Welcome to another episode of Five
Minute Physiology with Dr. Andy Galpin.
>> You might be surprised to hear this, but
there actually are many scientifically
validated ways to speed up or boost your
metabolism. Unfortunately, very few of
them will actually help you lose any
body fat. Confused? I don't blame you.
Most of the things I have personally
heard in this space are either outright
lies or completely exaggerated. Most of
the time is sell you a product. It is
true though. Some people have an easier
time eating as much food as they want or
seemingly so and staying lean while
others have a far more difficult time
losing body fat or maintaining where
they're at. So that is a real phenomenon
and it is tied to your metabolism but
not in the way you think. Trust me, as
someone who has a PhD in human
bioenergetics, I can tell you clearly
there is no such thing as a fast or slow
metabolism. So what's really going on
here? Let's really quickly unpack it and
let you walk away with some
scientifically supported ways to boost
your metabolism. Here's where things get
complicated. There are dozens of studies
showing a variety of products can
increase your metabolism. What they're
almost always looking at is what's
called your basil or resting metabolic
rate. Now, this is the amount of energy
you're producing every minute or second.
And this can be elevated with countless
things. spicy food, cold water, cold
air, caffeine, green tea, stimulants,
thermogenetics, sleep, acute exercise,
and so on and so forth. These will take
your metabolic rate from here to here
right now.
The problem is that may or may not
necessarily result in you losing any
more body fat because the amount of
change is small. The transient time
point, in other words, how long it's
elevated, tends to be within minutes or
hours at most. And so while you might
eat some spicy food and your basil
metabolic rate might go up five or 10
calories for 30 minutes, that's pennies
on what your entire body is holding in
terms of caloric load. So it's not going
to make any functional difference. You
also have an issue of sometimes we
result in a compensation mechanism in
which because you were elevated
slightly, your body will then match that
elevation with a down regulation to keep
your total net at the exact same level.
This is where marketing claims tend to
be confusing to the consumer because
they can say we ran a study. It was
third party validated, double blind,
placebo controlled, all the buzzwords.
And they're right. It did happen. And
that thing did result in a statistically
significant increase in basil metabolic
rate. But was it clinically or
practically meaningful for what you care
about body fat? Probably not.
Where this thing is real is the second
half of the equation and that is can I
do something that will permanently
elevate my basil metabolic rate. Another
way to think about this is can I be
burning more calories just sitting
around doing nothing and can this
caloric burn be in an amount that is
meaningful for me so after several weeks
or months I will actually lose some
physical weight. The list here goes from
dozens to just a couple.
Some things to focus on. The biggest
impact you'll make here by far with a
lot of literature with meaningful
effects is sleep. If you aren't sleeping
great, you need to look no further for
elevating and enhancing your metabolic
rate or boosting metabolism than
correcting that sleep issue. Even if
you're feeling sleeping okay and you can
go from that to great sleep, that will
have the biggest impact of anything I'm
about to say. After that, and I truly
friends mean way, way lower on the
priority list are things like adding
skeletal muscle. For every pound of
muscle you add, you will burn a small
number of calories per day. And that can
add up to a lot over years and months,
but it's not going to be the difference
of you losing two or three or 10 pounds
of fat in a month or something. It's a
very small amount. Now, this game is all
about stacking lots of small wins over
time, for sure. So, that's great. I want
you to add some muscle, but I also don't
want you to be thinking just because you
put on a few pounds, you're all of a
sudden going to lose all that extra body
fat because that's not likely to happen.
A couple of other things to throw out
here that have an actual quality
scientific evidence base are one, eating
more calories in general, and two, any
form of exercise. Now, to make sure
we're really clear here, if you do
something that gives you a short rise in
metabolic rate and you do it frequently
or consistently or it leads to more
energy expenditure overall, then that
will itself lead to more fat loss. But
it wasn't the fact that that thing
boosted your metabolism that did it.
Here's a direct example. Let's say you
ate some spicy foods or ingested some
caffeine, took some green tea or put
your face in cold water and that gave
you more motivation to go exercise. So,
you exercised harder or longer or more
frequently. You did it more
consistently. You had a better workout
or you felt better, so then you didn't
reach for more stimulants. So, then you
had a better night of sleep or you made
better nutritional choices. It's the
secondary or indirect effects of those
boosters that actually led to you taking
a better lifestyle action which then led
to eventual fat loss. So if any of you
have ever tried something like that or a
product in that realm and said, "I don't
know, it worked for me." It's probably
because it just helped you with
motivation. You actually felt better.
You went and then did something that was
the real cause of that change in energy
equation which helped the body fat come
up from the chronic perspective. Our
true ways there are fixing sleep, making
sure it's great, adding some muscle, and
then lastly, if you have any other
health performance anchor, so something
really going wrong in your physiology, a
clinical disease or even subclinical
one, those things can put constraints on
your metabolism as well, which might be
causing problems. In that case, you
don't need to do anything special except
for resolve or otherwise treat that
issue, and you should see your the basil
metabolic rate rise back up. If you like
this stuff and you want to learn way
more about it, I would encourage you to
check out episode 11 of my co-op podcast
called Perform with Dr. Andy Galpin
where I went through a full deep dive,
shared the exact research, covered way
more ground, other topics, other
protocols, and so you can see all that
available on YouTube and anywhere else
you get your podcast. Thanks so much for
checking out another episode of Fiveish
Minute Physiology, and I'll see you next
time. If you enjoyed this and want to
keep learning more about human health
and performance, consider signing up for
the Catalyst. That's my completely free
newsletter where we share information
about places I've learned from, great
books, podcasts, social media people to
follow, and other ways to stay upto-date
with the most recent evidenceinformed
approaches in this field. I'll put a
link to that newsletter in the
description below, as well as pinned to
the top comments, and I'll see you
there. Thank you for tuning in to
another episode of Five Minute
Physiology with Dr. Andy Galpin.